so welcome so welcome everyone to voices
with rebecky I'm joined again by my good
friend lemon Pascal some of you probably
saw the earlier discussion I had with
lemon lemon is an important figure
within the metter modern movement and if
you saw the last video you know he
brings a very eloquent and theoretically
sophisticated articulation to his
understanding and practice of meta
modernism and using that as a framework
with which to respond to issues such as
like the Kovach crisis and the meaning
crisis so welcome again I mean it's it's
really good to have you here really good
to see you again too John always nice to
talk with you
let me tell you what's been on my mind
this morning
they have you picked from among them and
will go down one of those pathways sure
sure sure so I'm thinking about how the
generalized set of shamanic practices
maps on pretty nicely to what the future
of humanity might need oh it's a lot
about the kind of the mechanics of split
attention mm-hmm how that applies to
developmental practice you know practice
I'm also thinking a lot about the danger
of superficiality and meaning making
dangerous shallowness of values and
whether things you know something
inhibits the process by which meaning
actually becomes an embodied experience
yeah now we could have all the tools of
meaning at our disposal but if it stays
at the surface what good is it all right
right right that's what's on my mind
today um well I find all of those
interesting so let's try and talk about
all of them but let's start with the
last one because it's always good to
start with meaning I think it's a good
it's a good place it usually sets up
your thinking for everything else so one
of those you know I think about this a
lot too and I get asked questions about
you know the dark side of meaning making
and and of course that's completely
relevant because I argue that the the
meaning making machinery is also the
self deception machinery this why this
is why I try to strongly
she ate an integrate meaning with wisdom
the cultivation of wisdom precisely
because I think the meaning making
machinery well it does give us the
connectedness the religio you know
kindness to herself each other in the
world that enhances meaning in life it's
also this very same machinery that
predisposes us towards bullshitting
ourselves and deceiving ourselves so
that's an argument I have for why I
think I don't think it's a metaphysical
necessity I think it's a practical
constitutive necessity that the
cultivation of meaning and the
cultivation of wisdom should be done in
a completely interdependent manner so
from your point of view what do you
think are the mechanisms involved in you
know there's this first step where you
recognize something you say hey that
could give me some meaning that's got
meaning all over it I agree I assert of
value or I perform a practice and it's
right there for me I could tell someone
else yeah but I've got this thing that's
enhancing meaning for me but how does
that what are the mechanics of embodying
that and taking that deeper and
assimilating that because it seems like
a lot of people stop at the first stage
somehow if that's the right metaphor
yeah I think that is it correct metaphor
and part of what's going on there I
think is modal confusion and I'm not
attributing this to you but it fits the
description or people get focused on an
experience they've had all right and
they have this object and the point
about that is I think that's that's well
first of all it's modal confusion you're
missing what is most important about the
experience and you're trying to have it
and recapture it again and again you're
missing the capacity to not look at it
but look through it and see what you can
learn from it that is transferable to
other situations and so you know this is
you know let me use you know a martial
art analogy like you find this stance
and you do this move and oh wow and you
just keep going back to that again and
again and again
that's actually not very good what you
need to do is try and spar with it right
trying spar with it put it into a
problem that is beyond the comfortable
zone that the experience is giving you
and see if it facilitates insight and
transfer and learning and a sense of
challenge for you in so far I mean the
Buddha warns about this you know
consistently and it's something that the
Western Buddhists don't pick up on you
are not supposed to be pursuing
contentedness or self-satisfaction or
even sort of wonderful feelings the
point about this right is transformation
the point about this is that you have
cultivated you realize in it a potential
for a skill that can be cultivated that
can be applied throughout your life you
shouldn't be pursuing contentedness that
that's you know he worries about you
know the contentedness of cabbages or
something like that there's a writer
just with people who and what they do is
they they get obsessed with it and I
mean that that's even in some versions
of the quest for the Holy Grail the the
quest is found not when they find the
object but when they realize what the
Grail stands for and how they're
supposed to change their whole view on
life in their whole way of being so I
think it's very important to do a lot of
practices that see if you can translate
it into well into a way of embodying it
but also much more importantly a way of
enacting it so for example let me let so
we're not talking just abstract
abstractly let me give one concrete
example of what I'm talking about so
it's very dangerous when people are
meditating to think that sort of where
the point is to get away from their life
and into this wonderful space and and
then they want to get back to there and
it can be a wonderful space right and I
really warn against that and I tell
people that what you need to do so when
you're coming out of the meditation you
have an additional practice all right
first all you're trying to integrate
what you've cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness and
cognition and one of the things we do is
we we we we practice
what traditionally calls the Five
Precepts but I turn them into the five
promises what you're trying to do is
you're trying to create salient Stags
areas important you know dimensions in
life in which you have opportunity to
integrate what you're cultivating in
your practice with your everyday life to
apply mindfulness to apply Metta and so
you know you and so you recite these
promises and the point of them one of
them is you know I promise not to speak
mindlessly very appropriate right now
but mindfully you know trying to you
know in remembrance of the being mode
cultivating wisdom because what that
should do is train people to remember in
the sense of saw team remember how
important speech is to personhood it's
the thing that most turns us into
person's most turns us into moral agents
has the capacity to alter our cognition
and dramatic ways and so it's reminding
you when you're speaking to go oh right
here's where I should be applying
mindfulness not drifting into idle
chatter or just spinning and part of
what that means even more concretely
within speeches am i practicing this
mindfully the cultivation of wisdom am I
am i listening am i entering into
genuine dialogue where am i just
monologuing so I'm trying to give you a
concrete example I think the principle
and practice of integrity which I offer
as a better virtue than authenticity I
think the practice of integrity it's
it's a practice it's literally a
practice of integration between your
practice and their everyday life you
need all kinds of integration practices
that's would be my answer then you're
trying to find situations where you can
apply the principle that you've already
accepted right and I like this thing
about the you know the orientation
towards comfort has a danger in it yeah
yeah it's very similar to saying people
are lazy because there's a I suspect
unnatural organismic reluctance to
engage in effort in general because it's
an energy expenditure I'm thinking of
there's a there's a beautiful like
historical moment where Noam Chomsky
defended this guy who'd written these
Holocaust denial
yeah reporter said to him you know why
did you do this and he said free speech
only applies to things that you find
abhorrent otherwise it's not even
invoked yet yeah right so there's a
there's a difficulty in embodying a
principle it's very easy to affirm a
principle and I'm assuming just because
we try to conserve system resources in
ourselves that we would be reluctant to
make the effort often that actually
would bring a meaningful value forward
into practice right and so that that
gets to the next things very much
I mean Stanovich Keith Stanovich they've
sort of the one of the premier research
surface on rationality talks about what
he calls the cognitive miser that the
brain is always trying to get as much as
it can for as little effort as it can
and the thing about that is you have to
practice active open mindedness you have
to keep noting instances where you're
doing that and then challenge it when it
becomes apparent that that often is you
know it's often locking you into
superficial short-term goals rather than
long-term deeper cause so you have to
practice that but let's let's go back to
the things that empower and encourage
people so you also teach people in this
practice of integration again I'll use a
Buddhist framework discuss if I started
there I'm not saying it's exclusive or
exhaustive or anything ridiculous like
that just using it because I've already
brought it up so it's good continuity so
you trained you you trained people to
also practice the Buddha the Dharma and
the Sangha the Buddha doesn't mean
learning about Saturday Gotama
that's not a waste of time that's a good
thing to do but what it means is when
you're doing those moments of
integration take note of them and I
literally mean take note of them write
them down and celebrate the moments of
insight so as you know if you keeping a
journal of all you where you've caught
yourself in self-deception you can just
expand this right don't just know where
you were self deceived and you sort of
realize it also note where you are
insightful or you you sort of cut
through to what was really the
zero most relevant so this is called
water in your Buddha it's like a plant
and we you have to act
we celebrate this so that it goes from
being something you enact to a presence
within you I'm not claiming anything
metaphysical here I'm just saying there
it starts to how it starts to get a
semi-autonomous you know your inner
teacher thing and that starts going the
Dharma learn I mean so for example read
some standard bitch learn about the
cognitive misers learn about it because
learning about this stuff first of all
it motivates your brain to open this the
scope of its predictions and its
anticipation and in addition to doing
that you know you're not at least part
of the resistance
- deeper practice is not ignorant at
least you can alleviate how that is
contributing to your inertia and then
the and the third is the same you've got
to do this is what I'm so interested in
dialectic and deal locus because you've
got to interact with other people who
are engaging in similar similar
practices this I mean this is this is
one of the tried-and-true things is why
you know well if you want to kick out
the whole ism you got to get together
with other people who are trying to kick
alcoholism if you want to lose weight
you got to get together with other
people who are trying to lose weight you
want to learn a martial art you have to
go to a dojo right this is a deep
principle we most of our best learning
is done within you know a participation
in distributed cognition so if people
start to practice and the thing about
these things is they they have although
I'm pitching them as instrumental they
also have intrinsic worth rewards for
them so it's nice to get that sense
celebrate that sense like it feels good
it's the brain goes whoo right and also
when you're learning new stuff you bring
those oh and you know and then meeting
with other people and experiencing what
you have aptly called overflow or at
least trajectory towards that is also
deeply deeply motivating to people and
so I think what you need to do is like
you have your practice sort of built a
model here then you have integration
practices the cultivation of integrity
and then you have these comprehensive
practices that are designed to keep you
aspiring and keep you motivated
I love all of that it sounds like it
applies very well to embodying a meeting
making principle yeah
well I'm also thinking about the
assimilation of perceptions hmm
right there's a I don't know how
familiar you are with your Jeff Ian's
but they have this beautiful phrase the
food of impressions sounds in US only as
dough and dough is the first note on an
octave of assimilation all right right
so that they there's a potential energy
and stimulation an incoming possibility
for salience now engage just by
beholding something but in general we
either get carried away by the next
perception or there's a kind of flatness
to our beholding so you know how do you
think of more deeply assimilating
perception so I've been putting a lot of
thought into that right now to in
connection with there's an interesting
synchronicity between us here yeah I've
been putting a lot of thought into that
because of dialectic and ear logos
because and this is actually germane to
what we're talking about and this is an
excellent point it's made by Christopher
Moore a belief or I think Sarah I'm a
wrap it makes the same point anyways
when when you're in you know Socratic
dialectic it's not just that arguments
are being compared the the deal logos
actually is an exemplification of a way
of life Socrates is actually
exemplifying a way of life and in in in
in comparison to other ways of life
because for Socrates ways of
argumentation and ways of life are bound
deeply together and then what you see is
but that's why beauty is invoked so
often beauty and love you know this is
one of Spinoza's great insights right in
the ethic he said you know the only
thing that will will you compete against
an emotion is another emotion all right
you can think all you want but if you
haven't cultivated love you doomed right
and I think that and Plato reports
completely consonant with that as well
and so I am getting to the point what
that all comes down to is you know the
role that the practice of the
beautification of a way of life and so
and and what that requires is that what
I think
in addition to you know the
practicalities of what I said there's a
philosophical critique that has to be
engaged in because of a cultural
misrepresentation han in his book saving
Beauty criticizes how we have reduced
Beauty right to because it the
aesthetics of the smooth we likes things
smooth and shiny because what we want is
we want things that in no way disrupt us
or disturb us we want things that are
readily and eat we want things we want
things to flow smoothly and we want we
were like smooth objects and we like you
know our technology to have a smooth
like an and he talked about the
aesthetic of smoothness and in any sets
and we confuse it with beauty we confuse
it with beauty we what we what we've
reduced Beauty to is ease of consumption
ease of use and that of course is to
remove a lot of what you know is central
to beauty we wait when you read other
people like Plato or you know Ellen
scurries book arm on beauty all right
there's this older sense of beauty that
is captured when like when we say we're
struck by beauty we're struck by it
right it's disruptive Rilke and one of
the elegies says you know beauty is the
sense of you know something like the
sense of terror of an angel that is
almost killing us right and so part of
what it is is to try to understand how
to beautify the serious play that is not
just training a skill but is cultivating
a an attractive way of life for yourself
and for other people
and so what that does I think what that
does is it starts to move us off of what
you I think you're calling a superficial
response to our perceptual experience
and it starts to move us towards you
can't you can't generate beauty but what
you can do is make yourself more and
more receptive and open to it and then
the way you relate to it
when it's when you experience it try to
see it's the exact opposite in Plato
right so our model funds right
consumptive model the smoothness for
Plato beauty is the doorstep to awe and
for Plato you don't consume Beauty right
beauty beauty inspires you to create he
says you want to give birth to Beauty
within Beauty the experience of beauty
is a genuine experience of the impulse
towards generativity and also it's
aspirational that the eros is no longer
consumptive eros its generative eros and
it's the move towards you know hopefully
generating for yourself and others a way
of life so I think really formulating
what Beauty means to us because it's the
normativity operating I think on our on
receptor or perceptual world the word
aesthetics relates to sensation right
I think rehabilitating and I mean that
in the sense of both reformulating yet
and make it making it habitable for us
again rehabilitating beauty and then
turning it into a practice where we
cultivate the receptivity to it and we
cultivate the responsibility to it the
generative response rather than the
consumptive impulse I think that's a
powerful way and you see it through
there lots of different thinkers
converge on this idea but like I said
Plato is in this respect my greatest
card so I think we just like I've been
trying to open up expand of the notion
of realness with the fork
of knowing I I think we need to get back
to beauty and in an in a way that
directly translates into the motivation
for wisdom you make me think of two
things and there's this there's this
tension in spiritual religious history
between the personal and the impersonal
force of course I very often very often
it's presented to us as a journey away
from the personal toward the impersonal
alright even as a journey away from the
embodied to the utterly abstract yeah
yeah and so there's a there's a way of
talking about consciousness practice
which is similar in wersal and that you
you should learn to pay perfect
attention to everything no matter what's
arising you're learn to practice
intentionally noticing anything and
these are really useful practices
however they're distinct from a practice
of impressions rather than perceptions
because the impression impresses you
you're struck by something that's
peculiar to your sense making system you
could practice attending mindfully to an
arbitrary stimulus on the other hand you
could practice attending to something
that your system has contributed to
evoking as a particular unique
impression of the world that stands out
to you and has come halfway to draw you
forward toward it yeah that's exactly
what I was trying to articulate with
with the notion of beauty so the
relevance realization machinery is sort
of in one direction it's making things
relevant to us but it's also that that
relevance realization machinery is a
vehicle through which a being can
realize itself put a demand on us so
these two I mean again we've got he sees
the beautiful torso of Apollo and what's
the final line of the poem you must
change your life you must change your
life that's you know and what's his name
yeah slaughter jerk you must change your
life is written a book about this in
response to the meaning crisis and
that's that's what I mean IIIi mean this
sense of what Beauty does is it
discloses it's like oh I didn't know
things could be this way right but it
also puts a demand on you it puts a
demand on you that I have to write I
have to as Plato says I have the demand
on you is you have to make yourself in
this zones and I do not mean this
cosmetically all right you have to make
yourself more beautiful right the the
proper response to beauty is to attempt
to conform to it just like the proper
response to any deep normative standard
like realness is attempt to conform to
it and so I think trying to give
priority let's put it that way giving
priority to the those moments of beauty
and perhaps they become experiences of
ah but moments where you feel this
simultaneous thing that the reality is
disclosing itself in new ways to you and
then there's a demand on you to
cultivate the skills that will maintain
the actualization of those new
opportunities not so that is how I
practice that is how I practice did that
interesting the smoothness thing is
interesting to me because I think you
know there's a critique there that's
completely valid but at the same time
smoothness is a pretty good definition
of beauty from one angle and that the
problem is nay not so much the
smoothness as laziness and passivity and
how we receive smoothness that we don't
have the energy or in Yashin to yet I
think the five things that don't
initially seem smooth yeah I think
that's Hans intent I don't I don't think
he thinks the property of smoothness is
itself intrinsically dilatory us or
anything like anyway there are things
that should be smooth the question many
things should and I've often reached for
that kind of a terminology to describe
states that I've been in you know
you fall into a state and fall us maybe
not the right word because you've worked
to get there but we're essentially the
seamless continuity of being is what
stands out to you in that experiential
moment the utter smoothness of
everything yeah and then when you've had
that you can look at anything and go
somehow there's a smoothness in there
even if it seems discontinuous to me
yeah possibility of experiential
smoothness that I've confirmed in some
other state yeah I think that's right
and I think well I mean I had some
concerns about when I was reading that
passage in HoN because of you know Tai
Chi Chuan and there's a sense in which
you're trying to get a particular kind
of smoothness and so that's why I
answered I think so readily to your
question I don't think it's smoothness
per se I think what he and he there are
things that I think should have the
aesthetic of smoothness I don't think he
would disagree with that either but what
he's what what what he's saying though
is that something else has been reduced
to smoothness which is beauty and beauty
isn't smoothness and it isn't reducible
to beaut it to smoothness and that and
so it's not the smoothness per se or
even an aesthetic appreciation for
smoothness in things or practices I
don't think that's what he's intending
to convey I think what he's intending to
criticize is the reduction of all of the
properties and all of the potential and
all of the power of beauty to the the
easily consumable smooth I think that's
the point he's willing to address yeah
there's a Tai Chi is interesting in this
respect because I think if a lot of
people imagine what beautifying their
lives would consist of they might
imagine themselves making movements more
in keeping with the Tai Chi style and
tempo yep that's there's something
really telling about that that we have
an intuition to move in that direction
of activity Oh
however there's also a danger of getting
trapped in the you know everything has
to be slow and sattvic yeah yeah yeah
yeah to me I'd like to use that as a
segue to one of the other topics
the blending of attention streams is
some great interest to me and one of the
things that is involved in the Taichi
tempo is a sort of balance split between
the part of you that's making the
activity and the party that's receiving
feedback from the activity at the same
moment and they get into a kind of
experiential parity which is your
internal cue that you're doing the
movements to your own satisfaction yeah
there's a blending of these two
attentions and there's a nice balance
between them and it seems like it pays
us back something as we undergo an
activity yeah because I think first of
all that's recognized in the tradition
your intuition is accurate Institute
which is no surprise you know you you
have a really good facility with looking
at phenomena and then intuiting and I
don't mean that in the romantic sense of
intuitive an important pattern the
principle therein in the tradition you
do they talk about the two eyes of
Taichi and and and and so let's play
with the matter one is the eye looking
inward sort of the introspective
introspective and an introspection and
interception are fused together looking
into your mind space and feeling into
your body space are fused together
that's the inner and then the outer is
the tiger eyes you're not fixating on
anything but you're you have an eye that
is like a tiger too hot it's flowing
over continually flowing over and then
the reason why they use the two eyes is
they're invoking the stereoscopic fusion
metaphor you get to a state where like
where they left and right you know how
the left and right visual fields are
fused to give you depth an added
dimension to your visual experience
that's the metaphor when you get that
when you get the inner right so first of
all there's the like I say you're
dropping below are sort of culturally
emphasized division between
introspection and into interception
you're trying to get the grounding
awareness in which they are together
indistinguishably interfused alright and
then you're like they say and then
you're fusing that right like in
stereoscopic vision
with the external thing and then that
gives you this it gives you a new depth
of experience that you can't have when
you're merely looking inward or merely
looking outward and I think that's
important because I mean I think that's
any enacted and expanded thing about
what I talked about in the series where
this model parties idea that ah that
perception is an action in which we are
trying to right find the optimal grip
and and where we move around it where
we're trying to get the sort of the
biggest possible de Stolte that doesn't
right lose too many details and try to
get too many details that doesn't get us
to close that we lose the gestalt and of
course there isn't there isn't an
algorithm for that because the
ultimately optimal grip is varying
according to the needs of the situation
right is very like if a device to repair
the button on here then the gestalt is
useless I need to I need to really focus
in but if I want to be using it right
I'm gonna have a different optimal grip
on it and I've I been looking for it in
my room right because I can't quite see
it different and so what that means
I think it's tying it all together right
I think what part of the experience of
beauty is the experience of a new way a
new kind of optimal grip and this also
goes back to my point that the relevance
realization the enhancement of it in
cultivating reverence and wisdom also
has to go with this divided attention
thing because it's like you're going to
find the optimal grip relative to what
you're finding most relevant but if your
relevance realization machinery is screw
it all over the place having you know
the the stereoscopically fused streams
of attention can still really massively
met mess you up you want an ultimate you
want an optimal grip the amount of
ultimate optimal grip not ultimate great
optimal grip to be deeply integrated
with you know an enhancement of your
capacity for zeroing in on relevant
information that's what I would argue at
least yeah I mean this this gripping
device here is useful
because it's very fluid it could be used
to grip in a vast array of circumstances
yes so it seems like we could easily get
trapped in a particular bounces of
attention but if we could diversify
weaponize that to be available to all
kinds of different scenarios then we'd
really have something well that's a lot
of different issues converge for me on
the notion of split attention because I
can see it underlying almost every kind
of historically proposed self
development or spiritual practice right
whether you're going to add an
additional point of focus into whatever
you're normally focusing on or whether
you're gonna try to bring mind and heart
together or whether you're gonna try to
balance self another in exchange or the
left and right brain or the you know all
these things involves some kind of
negotiated balancing that seems to pay
off more than you put into it gets an
overflow out of that kind of parity I
agree because I think all of those
things are various ways in which we're
playing with the salience landscaping
and identity forming of relevance
realization because relevance
realization is about a dynamical system
that ultimately balances between
opponent processing goals that are
opposite in some sense or a but are also
interdependent because they interact for
States and process it's not just goals
and so yeah I think I mean it I mean
even to embark on any kind of
transformation is going to put you into
that need to differentiate and integrate
your your attentional stream because
you're trying to you know you're trying
to couple your future self to your
current self if you're aspiring and if
you don't right and if you're self
regulating you have to expand your frame
so you can pay attention to the deep
future and then zoom in to see what's
really deeply happening right now all of
these things involve that kind of
process and I think that's a way in
which we train and it's a train train
but like also inhabited we don't quite
have a verb for doing that but
but the cognitive flexibility which is
so predictive of you know insight being
able to get into the flow state being
able to through it you know deal with
complex novel situations yeah I think so
and I think you know training those
training the complexification of
attention that's basically what we're
doing we're differentiating it and then
reintegrating that's how we get emergent
attention attentional capacities I think
I don't I'm saying this I'm not just
missing your point I'm trying to say I
think it's almost inevitable because if
we want to get new functions we have to
complexify other functions together and
I think that's what I think that's what
you're pointing to self-regulation seems
like a really key part of this because
on one of the areas where this shows up
is a real concern is in I mean what we
call cognitive dissonance when somebody
who's inhabiting a space between two
different pressures or strategies or
perspectives and something in us rejects
that space we want to fall back onto a
simpler model so in order to stay there
you need not only the idea that you want
to stay there but you need to be able to
self-regulate in order to not have a
phobic response to the tension between
if the yeah attentional possibilities
you're gonna try to integrate I think
that's right um and you know and again I
think we've circled back to an earlier
theme in in a helpful way because part
of that is to get you know to remember
to realize because beauty is exactly
that kind of thing I think it's the it's
an experience of something novel
unfamiliar but it's it has a potential
to be drawn into our current world and
transform it beauty is a way in which we
can learn to be positively disposed
towards liminal uncertainty as opposed
to the brains natural initial impulse
which is whew I don't like that that's
really unfamiliar I can't predict
what's gonna happen here right and
what's really interesting about this is
especially you know when this
constellation of things Beauty Wonder
and awe think about oh it's so all
should be one of the worst experiences
that people have because when you
measure what they say is you know I I
get a sense of vastness and
incomprehensible 'ti and I feel so small
and powerless well if I just induced
that in you you'll usually freak out
right but right and that's why I can get
can pass over into horror but ah is
actually experienced by people as so
powerfully motivating that it is one of
these experiences not perfectly not
algorithmically that has a strong
tendency to motivate people to
longitudinal transformation and change
so there's something in us there's a
potential there's an aesthetic potential
within us I think this is one of Plato's
insights that we can nurture and
cultivate we can practice it so that
when something comes up right we can
move into that integration that
complexification rather than backing
away right into the familiar zone of
comfort so again I hope I'm not
repeating myself but I'm trying to show
you what what the connections are I
think yeah I think they're the flipside
of the same experience you know with the
more you learn that component the more
your brain is likely to recognize them
when it sees the frustrated version yeah
you're a half a step away from the
exalted version yes it's private
no no coincidence that we use some of
the same language for you know religious
and even sexual ecstasy that we use for
massive unacceptable thwarting yes yes
yes yeah we reach for the same words
well it's even in related words we have
the word awesome but we also have the
word awful because it has that but you
see
I so this is much more speculative on my
part um I think part of why we have an
aesthetic for this is places where
things that are that we have a de cotta
me between but and we realize that
actually they're interdependent and
opponent right these are these are
places of Kairos these are places of
criticality where these are actually
opportunities for significant
developmental change and so again I
think we we have so I think we have two
choices about that we can be passive and
you know
well maybe three choices let me try we
can be passive and just say well I'm
just gonna wait for those events but
then when they happen you're not really
not going to be able to you know
properly assume so many traditions say
practice on little things where there's
nothing major happening so when the big
thing happens you're ready to go because
if you try and cultivate it when the big
things happen you're pretty much gonna
get screwed right now the flip side is
also mistake well I'm gonna make I'm
gonna secure Lea Activision I'm gonna
make Beauty appear before that's not
gonna work either so this is why again
I've been doing so much work on this
notion of participatory knowing right
because one one of the functions
I think of participatory knowing that I
haven't talked that much about but I
it's in my thinking and I want to bring
it up is how it precisely steers us
between the skillet and Charybdis of
passivity pure passivity and pure
activity and it gets well it gives me
participation and and this was really
emphasized emphasized in all the
traditions and it's enough something
that lends book right trying not to try
right where you're trying to find and
right effort right and all this sort of
stuff and so I think you have to
cultivate a deep capacity for recognized
and even beautified participatory
knowing so that you come into those
Kairos with the set of skills you need
but also the proper existential mode for
or relating to them do you think these
disruptions are I don't want how to say
this all of equal size right when you
say awesome and awful one sounds like
it's full of all and the other one
sounds like it has some aw in it which
might be the amount as opposed to a
complete overload so are these are these
situations where there's a sort of
absolute overwhelm in which you could go
either way with it or is it more like
there's too much of it sometimes and
other times it feels like almost too
much but really it's a manageable amount
or it's at the edge of your assimilation
capacity yeah and I think that's what
Marilla was trying to get at in the in
the dunya ology is right it's it's on
the and Fischer talks about that in his
book wonder the rainbow and the
aesthetics of rare experience where he
says what they do is they put you on
what he calls the horizon of
intelligibility they put you into that
place and is this you know I call it the
trans world it's not like an other world
it's a place between two different you
know existential worlds right and you're
in you're there you're right on the
horizon and intelligibility you can
still you can still feel backwards to
where you are currently but you also
have a port ending and a portal right
those words are related for a reason
right and so I think I think that it's I
think it's more like beauty it is
something where we have a saw and you
know I'm working with Jennifer stellar
and Michele Ferrari and Jensen Kinlan is
but ah seems to me to be an indication
of that you've got not an optimal grip
on the phenomena because that's emerging
but that there is speculation on my part
but I think there's some sort of
cognitive mechanisms that it that sort
of tracks and says your complexify in
the face of this and it's starting to
clear the signal keep going versus ah
right no it's not complexified it's not
gelling signal is not clearing and I
think that's when you start to move in
horror I think part of what influence
that is not only our optimal grip on the
world but our our optimal grip on our
seeing of the world
this is prospect and refuge theory right
the the womb with the view is it
sometimes called so we are there's a
certain aesthetics of participating in
an environment that are important we
want to see as much as we can while
being seen as little as we can because
the first will help us find prey and
right and the second one will help us
avoid predation right and so again you
have to you have to you have to sort of
there has to be or not only an optimal
grip on whatever the our field thing is
there has to be or a sense that your
complexify towards an optimal grip I
think you have to have a current optimal
grip of like how you're seeing you're
saying like so for example a concrete
example you're much more likely to get
ah as opposed to horror witnessing a
stupendous lightning storm if you're
standing on your balcony but if you're
out in the open field that's a lot more
oh no right because you're deeply
exposed deeply vulnerable so I think I
think there's a really there's a finesse
to toggling between getting an optimal
drift on whatever the thing is it right
and also that is being that this optimal
grip and the optimal grip on sort of my
placement in the environment if you get
those two together in there in sync I
think that's what takes you more towards
ah right if you if you if you've got a
back of an optimal grip but there's
nothing in that much amazing happening
here you probably feel mild anxiety so
did that did that answer your question
yeah I think so if I even remember what
the question was what is their question
the question was well you know what I
thought was in terms of seeing as much
as you can while being seen as little as
you can
yeah right now
like being an audience member Inc of
yeah yeah
Nietzsche's first book about the
Dionysian festivals and the birth of
tragedy and his critique of Aristotle's
notion of tragedy because you know he's
telling a story there of these ancient
people gathering as the audience around
this young religious festival that we
might call an entertainment festival
today yeah and his critique of Aristotle
is that he says Aristotle is too focused
on the pathos that people were having
going through these bad experiences and
Nietzsche says no if you were in the
right state if you were robust if you
had the right philosophy if you were
hearty then you're not experiencing the
death of the hero as a tragedy you're
having fun watching a piece of
entertainment you're reveling in what
appears to be a tragedy assuming you're
coming from the right embedding to
handle that right I agree with that but
Nietzsche also I mean part of one of the
main themes of the birth of tragedy from
this period of music is that the tragedy
is a particularly powerful object right
you know not just in the cognitive sense
not I don't mean I could think the
tragedy come right it you could what you
have is you have the Apollonian hero
right and but you have the Dionysian
chorus and he you know and his
philosophy as you know it's all about
and here we're back to idiot it's all
about finding a dynamic optimization
between the Apollonian and the Dionysian
these critique of Socrates which i think
is misplaced by the way is that socrates
overemphasize the Apollonian at the
expense of the Dionysian um so III do
think that you there both of what I just
said
are there so part of what the prospect
and refuge thing does is it interacts
with right two senses of realness that
we have the Apollonian a sense of
realness is things are real when they
are confirmed when they're firmed
together where there
coherent right and the dynein is know
things are most rap most real to you
when they catch you by surprise
and and by the way people do do that
they do use those two different
different standards of realness in a
practical sense they you know what makes
sense and they can confirm that's what's
most real and then that which catches
them Supremes you know by deep surprise
is actually what's real and and the
reason is even though that's there they
are not logically identical they are
again stereoscopic you need both of them
for getting closer to realness if you're
if you if you don't ever have the
coherence in the confirmation then
you're not picking up on any patterns
you're just right but right if you never
are if those patterns are never broken
by the Dionysian then you're gonna get
ossified and locked in and so again III
think that right the prospect and refuge
yeah that you you want you do want to be
able to have the right relationship to
the unfolding and and art I see your
point
art is a very powerful way of giving us
prospect and refuge on something
beautiful I agree with that I think
that's a profound point but I want to
emphasize that even within tragedy you
see this theme we're talking about about
try and and what's really interesting I
think and this wasn't explored enough um
I think well maybe has I haven't read
all the scholarship on the birth of
tragedy but Nietzsche was really and
this is what I think it was this is a
theme you can see some of his team's
drift away and drop away but this theme
of the integration the complexification
of the Apollonian and Dionysian runs
through him completely and that's on the
horizon of intelligibility that's the
place between the Apollonian confirmed
you know where you cook you know safety
and the Dionysian prospect of challenge
and change yeah he's it's a very yes
definitely not my favorite of his books
but there's something in there that
that's at the core of his thought and is
particularly relevant I think still
going forward I agree with you is his
critique of Socrates
he's using Socrates to exemplify
something that happened historically and
I think he's picking on Socrates
unfairly because he's trying to overcome
his own initial love of Socrates so he's
struggling I think he's quite right to
call for a musical Socrates yes yes and
I think that in that that idea of the
interplay of the dynasty and in the
Apollonian and the idea that that can be
brought forward to us in art and
entertainment so that we can see this
process unfold and even see the central
representative of our coherent meaning
making be taken to pieces and then
somehow come back together and and live
to fight another day
I think that's a huge thing culturally
for us to learn this process right in
religious groups or philosophical groups
you could communicate very openly about
it yeah but in general people would need
to see the pattern happen many times to
start to assimilate it I would guess I
think this is very interesting what
you're saying and you know about the
aesthetics because it leads me to you
know this idea that you know that might
be a way again not exclusive or
exhaustive but an interesting way of
trying to distinguish art from
entertainment well maybe entertainment
is the aesthetics of the smooth and
there's nothing wrong with entertaining
right but maybe art is the aesthetics of
wonder in the way we're talking about it
here like you know suck you know in that
symposium Socrates talks about how what
he's Metaxa and also how love is attacks
ooh arrows because right if we could
because we try to get again on that
horizon of intelligibility right when we
when we love something beautiful we love
it precisely because we're not
completely conformable to it right well
there's a lack that you know when we see
something beautiful in a way it awakens
a sense of lack in us right arm and but
also right but but there's also you know
it impels us forward
it gives us some sense it's so
interesting I have in my in my with my
signature thing the script under my
signature and in Gmail you know that
love is its own kind of its own way of
knowing and where the and it's it's the
noticing kind of knowing because it's
really interesting how love gives you
simultaneously the sense of something
you lack which is you know the prospect
but it also gives you some intuition
that it's it is achievable for you or
knowable to you you can enter into a
proper relationship to it and I think
that's exactly a place where you're
gonna find real deep integration of the
sakra of the Apollonian
and the Dionysian and Socrates is all
about that kind of love he deeply deeply
is and that's what I thought so I think
Nietzsche deeply misses I think we write
because Nietzsche famously says I hate
Socrates he's so close to me I'm always
fighting him and so uh but I I'm just
giving my I think a you know a specific
argument to your point that I think
Socrates emphasis on an agogic love
right the transfer more transformation
of eros into an agog a the ascent right
is clearly where his love is a place
where we most deeply fuse the Apollonian
and the Dionysian and love is the proper
love and reverence are the proper
response to beauty let me throw in a
segue anecdote here it's a segue or our
continuation I'm not sure I'm thinking
of a time that I went to an art exhibit
with my father in Vancouver and upstairs
was a bunch of conceptual art pieces
mostly by Young University art students
right and not that that can't be an
amazing thing but it sort of leaves you
each one you look at and go is this art
I'm not sure what art is what is art is
the question it's time and downstairs
was the Rodin exhibit yeah and when you
see a piece of Rodin or in a room full
of them you don't think what is art you
think oh my god
what the hell is this what was this guy
trying to do there's astonishing quality
to it a real surprise in disruption and
a demand right it demands something from
you like because I was murder Fox load
that and the sovereignty of the good it
demands your attention not not you know
in some sort of animistic sense but it
demands your attention in that part of
the realization is the realization that
it is do a particular kind of effort and
do a particular kind of attention and
and that again I think it is that is
that generative sense of beauty that I'm
talking about rather than the
consumptives very much where I wanted to
go with that because I'm thinking of it
in terms of time frames ah there's a
form of art where you go oh yeah sure
that's neat and and everyday you see it
after that you're less impressed yeah
and there's this other form where
initially all you're confronted with is
the demands and every time you see it
you're more and more impressed you see
more and more about it there's a as an
analogy there with addictive flow States
which I know is something you're
concerned with because there's this
initial feedback that yeah upfront and
it starts to trail off yeah and there's
this other kind where there's an initial
demand and it builds up yes I think so
so if you take a look like scurries
notion of beauty she talks about how it
trains us for truth and justice the
experience of beauty it actually trains
us and that's what exactly we're talking
about here right and she so she does
this thing where she says you come upon
a tree and it's really beautiful and
then so so part of it is a kind of mmm
what I want I can call mortis there's
more two trees that I have previously
realized right so there's this aspect of
it that's very jet that encompasses all
trees and you've now seen something
about all trees there's a mourneth but
then she said I'm using my language not
hers but she points out but then we're
also struck by the
hilarity of it what the Buddhists would
call the suchness of it that that the
way it's presented to us as it has a
kind of uniqueness and irreplaceable 'ti
and unrepeatable 'ti about it and so
again I think I think beauty is playing
between those two things it's giving us
two senses of how things can be beyond
our categorical scheme one way it can
put us into sort of combinatorial
explosion right oh wow Wow
so much more right but then there's
there's also you know the the the the
non categorical identity of everything
that beyond all of the ways in which
it's belongs to categories this is its
own particular well it's the Buddha
States it's such an astute on it is to
put it into a category you have that you
know you have those those moments I
think in art - um well you really you
see something right I didn't realise a
tree could be like that right and then
also right you realize there's there's a
there's something non-repeatable in this
moment that I shouldn't be trying to
repeat because if I try to repeat it I'm
gonna lose it
so I think what happens right is when
the way it gets repeated is not
repetition it's like instead what we
talked about before with sacredness
that's the and I think this is what you
mean like here suppose it's a work of
art you you you what you do is it
transforms you you go out into the world
right and then when you come back you
see something in it you hadn't seen
before again you're not repeating the
experience what you're doing is you're
repeating the trend the process of
transformation and I think we shift off
back to the beginning again trying to
repeat the experience rather than trying
to cycle the transformation I think
that's again that's what we need to be
doing and that really ties in again to
this other sense of beauty that I'm
trying to talk about and love yeah
addiction definitely has this
diminishing returns problem with the
attempt to repeat the initial experience
as as validly beautiful as that initial
experience might have been for the
person right it's interesting with the
tree you know the the notion of the I
thou relationship yeah because I like I
never knew that about a tree before I've
got the first and third person in there
but in perceiving and this to me goes
back to what I was talking about about
the assimilation of perceptions this
tree strikes me and I'm partly looking
at it's the unique intactness of its
wholeness at the moment which is
something I'm cognitively sculpting out
of reality to some degree right but
there's a there's like a next note right
if that's doe Rea then maybe there's a
me there's this next stage where it's
like the tree begins to lurk where it
has this withdrawn quality this other
Nassif I'm in dialogue with it
yes right we're not necessarily speaking
but me and the tree are kind of being
balanced in my experience totally gauche
meeting now but that's the heart of
gnosis right the heart of participatory
knowing that you know you you you you
you know the tree by becoming sort of at
one with the tree you right you you sort
of you're sort of personifying the tree
but also tree of finding yourself in
this resonant cycle so that more of the
tree is being disclosed to you and more
of you is being disclosed to you but
again not categorically but it but you
know I want to say expressively in but
in collingwood sense what people will
hear romanticism but it's being
expressed to you as you said in the
being mode it's doing the reciprocal
opening very much very much and so the
notion the notion that comes out is a
notion I've been talking a lot about
recently is right trying to bring back
the notion of faith not as the assertion
of belief but as the coupling of the
emergence of mind to the emergence of
the world that puts us into ongoing
right relationship with reality so the
model I have here is
my faithfulness to my partner is not to
hole is it's precisely not to hold an
unchangeable set of beliefs about her or
to try and completely grasper or have it
fixed it's instead to get into a
resonant adaptivity with her so that as
she changes I can afford that and I can
adaptively change with her it's a
continuity of contact it's a it's a co
emergence there right a sense of
faithfulness rather than an
assertiveness and I think when people
have this you know where Beauty
motivates them in love to be faithful to
something like a text or a work of art
mmm I think we're getting into the realm
of the sacred now I really do I agree
with all that I think you know the
resonance that's implied by fidelity but
here's something I think about a lot
which is one of the basic shamanic
skills I would say is proprioceptive
imagination oh they're not yes I thought
that immediately when you were talking
about you know the tree becoming you yes
yeah because if you try to imagine what
it feels like to be the tree or the
Jaguar or whatever you have a real it
seems to me you have an edge in terms of
the skills necessary to undergo these
experiences we're talking about and so
that the whatever allows people to be
more capable in terms of interception at
proprioception probably sets them up to
be able to have more of these
experiences I agree I mean so you know
shamans I mean this is why there's a
long tradition of shape-shifting with
shamans right
precisely because and I talked about
this in the series so not only at the
spiritual value of being able to get
into this gnosis with things this has
practical value the shaman who is the
shaman you have to remember it's like
you're taking your glasses off and
looking at them and then you put them
back on and see if you look different so
the shaman has a participatory knowing
in act serious play what it is to be the
dear
and that will often help him be really
good at tracking the deer and so you get
this corrective loop and if he tracks
the deer better right it's Anna guarding
that feeds back into well that worked
and you know and so the and then you get
to cycling so you know shamans seem like
almost have you know miraculous tracking
abilities because they can really get
into the head of the animals that their
right um that their well doing this kind
of participatory knowing with so I think
participatory knowing yes has tremendous
spiritual potential but I think we
particularly cultivated it because it
was both socially that's doing this with
other people by the identifying with
other people is really important and I
think it was also really adaptive when
we were hunter-gatherers it's really
powerfully adaptive for us um so I think
that's why we carry around this
machinery and we try to exact it into so
many different situations I I wonder how
far back it goes you know because it's
not difficult to imagine that at some
extremely primitive level that this is a
useful skill even for a plant or a
protozoa to be able to sort of to feel
its way into the shape of something else
which you know every plant has to do
that with its niche yep um well I don't
know about the sentience of plants it's
up in the air that would I do think
there's I so I'm caught between two
things as you know in my work I really
emphasize deep continuity between us you
know and Nietzsche said this bring back
meat you know the height of my
spirituality reaches into the depths of
my sexuality right so I agree with the
deep continuity but I think we need to
remember something about us we we are
the most self malleable creatures on the
planet we often think about that you
know cognitively we're but even have
bodies like we transform our bodies in
ways in which other organisms just
don't do that right and our bodies are
sort of multi-up for being trained in
too many different kinds of niches
it's a weird and so and I think those
two are not disconnected the
malleability of our mind the
malleability of our body I think are
really important so while I do agree
with the deep continuity I think there's
something is especially important about
us there's an important difference this
we sort of about a neon tech you know
amplification of both cognitive and
physiological malleability and we're so
a part of the physiological malleability
of course is you know interacting with
tools and things like that but we're so
weird that way like imagine if we found
a bunch of chimps training for racing
something like what are they doing
they're trying to build muscles and
coordination patterns so that they can
run faster than they're then they're
here than their coworkers and what that
would freak us out only we do that kind
of stuff yeah it's uh it's a little bit
fanciful but to imagine the rest of the
ecosystem observing us beginning to be
beginning to prep for things you think
going forward in civilization you know
politically and ecologically and
economically and everything we have to
face going forward whether this requires
an increase in our malleability or not
yeah I think so so let's do the shamans
again because they're very helpful you
know the work from what Michael Weyman
Michael welcome and others especially
Matt Rossano
whole host of people if I mean it looks
like you know shamans are often a small
percentage in your population something
like somebody was quoted a four percent
to me and I took I take the person
seriously but I haven't been able to
track down a specific reference but that
seems anyway is not problematic you know
most of the people in your group aren't
Shona well what was really important
about them and this is matress a nose
argument he's our biggest advantage
when we almost disappeared as a species
somewhere between a hundred thousand and
seventy thousand years ago right because
we really bottleneck we were dropped our
numbers drop dramatically and he argues
because there's there's good
archaeological evidence that of course
we started to evolve more cognitive
flexibility and we started to evolve art
and stuff like that so that's all
constant we're saying but he also
emphasizes that the shamans what they
what they did is they develop that they
develop their shape-shifting their
identity malleability because they're
the people that helped set up the trade
networks and that was our best that was
our big and best response we what we do
is we open up the economy of our
existence so that we are not we're not
bound to just the local environment
where we are so the shamans because of
their shape-shifting ability were able
to mediate between different communities
which is a freaking ly weird thing we
are again civilization is the skill of
living with strangers millions of them
all right
uh and so they were able to mediate
their material shape-shifting
malleability actually afforded
integrations between communities and
that's exactly what we need right now
that's exactly what we need right now we
need people who are much more we don't
need everybody to do that that's why I
did their little preamble about the
percentages but we need a significant
percentage of people that are recognized
for this role and start to undertake it
and be you know supported in some way by
the society I don't mean by the state
but by the Society for undertaking this
task yeah I think that's I think that's
what we need we need cyber shamans or
something like that right where that
that skill of being able to integrate
across domains um I sometimes in in a
playful manner I think you know that
being a cognitive scientist is kind of
like being a shaman because I have to
develop the capacity to integrate across
these different worlds these different
disciplines that you speak different
languages and have different customs and
different ways of gathering their
evidence and and so I do think that
finding individuals who have the
capacity for that kind of
malleability and synoptic integration
yeah I think that's crucial going for it
I thought I would be stronger I don't
see how we're going to get through all
of this unless we have more individuals
like that that are recognized and are in
some way supported by their society yeah
there's definitely the synoptic capacity
is huge I think in what the shaman does
there's this other thing of being
something of a professional outlier oh
yes right and how do you set up an
institution in which the professional
outlier of the village is taken
seriously on topics that are significant
to the villagers now I don't know if you
saw World War Z yes yeah but there's a
beautiful part in there where the the
Israelis built an anti zombie wall yeah
cuz they have military doctrine called
the tenth man where if if nine guys
agree the 10th guys supposed to disagree
and start acting on his disagreement
right so the first time guys go
yeah there's no zombie attack coming
that's preposterous the 10th man is
supposed to take that seriously and
begin preparing for the zombie attack so
he's a situation which there's an
institutionally valued outlier which
seems to be part of what the ancient
role of shamanism right now we have a
problem where a lot of the things that
are really significant to the unfolding
of culture outside of one say election
cycle or business cycle these things are
being spoken of by people who are a bit
like outliers yeah but they're not
folded into the heart of our
institutions we're not taking action on
that information we're not valuing the
outlier institutionally in the right way
yeah it seems to be very problematic
yeah I think that's right I think that's
that's why I think that judge completely
with the point I was trying to make
about the fact that we neglect and
marginalize these people it's also that
we've we've lost the the connoisseurship
you know the the discriminating
awareness to be able to distinguish
these people from people are gorgeous
not be
messed up or or or or trying to con us
right you know so we we don't want we
don't want to mistake the criminal for
the shaman and we don't want to mistake
the psychotic for the shaman and so
because we have we used to train
individuals think about this we used to
train individuals in that discernment
right so there was an apprenticeship
that you know the shamans were good at
finding the other people that would be
shamans right and that was part of their
job and the same thing you know it used
to be within the church you know this is
the churches of course subject to all
kinds of critique sir but you know do do
the church for a very long time was
successful did he knows things at times
but so has every institution like the
state and the market do so I'm not
picking on the church but I was I'm
thinking about how the church was able
to cycle between the mystic right and
the priests right so the priest
represents the orthodoxy block but the
church found mechanisms of sainthood
right and setting up new orders of monks
you know it found ways of trying to
manage those if sorry that sounds like
it was being purely instrumental I think
there was genuine love at times but it
found ways of getting these people into
kind of like you said they are validated
by the culture without the demand that
they become completely conforming to
sort of the standard norm so we have
been well I mean we're never perfectly
successful at this because we're also
human beings that we we were prone to
envy and pride and you know and doing
nasty things to each other so I'm not
speaking when they in some sort of rows
with rose-colored glasses but I mean
that that lasted for a long time right
the ability to venerate the mystic and
and give a place for that challenging
voice within a long-standing traditional
institution so
we can do it we can do it interesting to
me about that is because it's happened
so many times it seems like it's not
dependent upon us remembering to do that
but rather like when things are going
well we spontaneously do it and when
things aren't going well we do the
opposite right if there's some basic
condition of healthy social organization
and healthy bodies healthy minds and
whatever that is all together you might
say that that leads us to incorporate
and take advantage of something that
we've been doing all along and and
there's some process that goes wrong
which leads us to not do that instead to
not just not incorporate the outlier but
to fall back into a purity and
homogeneity mode yeah if the problem is
too much complication and we'll just
start cutting ourselves until we get
down to an adequately homogeneous so
yeah and and I think that's you know
that goes towards the the idea of
scarcity mentality so people do that
thing you're just describing typically
when they are well whether in the
scarcity mentality where some highly
valued thing is is is diminishing for
those people obviously you know it could
be things like food or water or security
but it can also be things like you know
meaning or participation a sense of
belonging to a group these are all
things that if people are starving for
them and I think ins sort of you know
maybe Maslow or Aristotelian sort of
hierarchy of needs but as what if people
are starving for them I think that they
do
that's what scarcity mentality shows
people do this under scarcity mentality
because this is to get you to try and
hoard and exploit what is closest to you
because it has a higher it has it has a
probability of one for close to one
because it's near you right where is
that long-term stuff
oh now the probability is low and that
when it's scarce if it's scarce here
it's probably not gonna be not gonna be
found there at all so I better horde
what I have here now and ration it out
for myself and the people I want to
survive so I think scarcity mentality is
really relevant to what you're saying
and then that means we need a culture
that is much more concerned with
alleviating scarcity mentality in many
many different domains and that's a
different way of thinking about the
function of governance right there's a
there's a full circle back to
superficial meaning making here because
if you confront a piece of art that you
don't immediately know what you're
supposed to do with it right then
there's a scarcity there and you might
recoil right rather than thinking that
there's an investment you can make and
at the same time you could have as we
all do now and you know the hyper
somatic digital environment there's an
immense number of incoming information
streams yeah but if we're if we're not
assimilating that and even though we
have all this data
we're undergoing a meaning scarcity yes
basically there's a scarcity of
understanding which makes us behave
reactively and acquisitive lee and it
might even create this vicious circle
where you then try to get more
information and you still don't get any
sense of meaning so you don't escape so
you try to get more information are you
trapped yeah I agree I think that's I
think that's very much you know a modal
confusion around information yeah very
very much and you sort of get like junk
attention because you paint you're
paying more and more attention to more
and more information but you're not
acquiring understanding or knowledge or
even wisdom yeah I I think that's that
very much is happening for us as a
culture it probably is one of the fuels
of conspiracy thinking because I think
people are if they sense that there's a
very natural impulse and in a way a
healthy impulsed to say I need to
Eve a whole bunch of this together
someone else yeah need a more synoptic
gaze yeah and I may be doing it out of
this scarcity mode and therefore I'm
failing and I'm grasping at things too
fast and I'm not betting the information
properly it's actually a pretty good
impulse to try to get this
interconnected even mythologically
resonant overview of what's happening
when you're faced by endless incoming
information streams yeah I agree with
that I mean I've talked about the rise
of conspiracy theories during this
crisis the Cova crisis there was a video
it's not up there anymore that I did for
rebel wisdom David took it down not
because he doesn't like the video but
because he's involved in investigating a
conspiracy theory right now well right
or sorry he's involved in investigating
an individual who uses conspiracy
theories in order to manipulate and
exploit people and so and he's doing
good work about that but I've talked a
lot about how you know conspiracy
thinking it just and there's
experimental work to validate exactly
what you said if you put people in
situations where they feel like they're
losing control they are much more likely
to see losery patterns much more likely
to accept conspiracy theories very very
much so
scarcity of control it is really
important and not in the sense of
mastery but the sense of being able to
interact effectively is definitely
predictive and you know and what you
said getting looking for a predictive
pattern is what is the brain's initial
response you know and and we're disposed
to you know to be overly vigilant for
agents in our environment again prospect
and refuge is anybody watching me is
there anybody behind the trees right
that's also that I think Inspira see
theories tap into all kinds adaptive
machinery that has been constellated
together into a very powerfully
maladaptive and self-perpetuating and
self-defending dynamical system within
people's cognition I call it a parasitic
processing and I think that's very much
the case now
the problem with people sometimes humid
doing that part of what happens is like
this is the thing I do that pisses off
the most people were generally because
one group of people are pissed off
because I've sort of challenged their
their particular conspiracy theory I
don't care if I upset them because I
think they need to be upset but there's
other groups of people who say but there
have been conspiracies right like I
don't want to I don't want to and you
know I don't want to miss the real ones
and I think that's the that's a better
way of framing this it's like well what
are the best tools for distinguishing
the losery conspiracies from finding the
real ones I think I think and it's a lot
about again learning to pay attention
the right way discern you know yeah you
practice in areas where you can check it
practice the skills in the little right
we're safe where you can check it and
then gradually see if they're
transferable right etcetera etcetera
yeah I when I think of conspiracy
theories which are very easy to dismiss
as if they were a homogeneous mass yeah
I always say to myself like one in ten
one in ten conspiracy theories is
correct I just don't know which one and
at the same time there's another
conspiracy that isn't mentioned in
anybody's theory that's too strange yeah
they haven't thought of it doesn't fall
within their paradigms and it's real as
well not be you know discernment is
invoked by both those positions yeah
what you see addressed in me was the way
we grasped for something out of scarcity
and the possible ways of channeling that
or using it productively like I do
breath holding and cold showers and I
know you're probably familiar with the
Zen parable of the master who holds his
students head under the water yeah and
he says you know what do you want
enlightenment as much as you want air
then you'll have it there's this
application of a petition that a
scarcity could be used to produce if
it's used within the right framework
yeah fasting fasting is the you find
fasting not only of food but from sex or
sleep
strategies used throughout the world
because I think that's where we can use
scarcity as a disruptive strategy which
and you know shamans make terrific use
of disruptive strategies because I see
because as I would argue we have
increasing evidence that getting the
right amount of disruption and
distraction into your problem framing is
provocative of insight and so or in
machine learning you know you let the
you know you let the neural network run
for a while and then you throw some
noise into it because that way it
doesn't over fit to its particular set
of data it allows it to generalize and
become more resilient and pick up on
right other things are there patterns
are there other other places in the
state space of possibilities um please
don't think it also increases the amount
of orgy that we are investing in our
active perception mechanisms it can I
mean scarcity can be something that
motivates people it energizes them but
scarcity can also erode their sense of
agency think about that narrowing it can
be a reciprocal narrowing like you get
with the addict and they it becomes
inconceivable that because the Attic is
living with a perpetual kind of scarcity
right but the Attic is the the the world
can't be any different than it is and
the addict can't be any different than
they are so there you know scarcity can
also drive reciprocal narrowing into
which people get kind of a learned
helplessness right I've learned
helplessness so yeah this is why I mean
it's it's a powerful disruptive
technique which is again why you see it
cross culturally cross historically but
it's also a particularly dangerous one
and this is why it's woven into you know
you know you the classic example the
buddha tries asceticism and rejects it
right precisely because the it's not
clear that using scarcity a disruptive
strategy it's not clear that the
benefits always outweigh the costs this
I mean last time we talked about
my sense of how spirituality and
religion are done through integrative
production of overflow but how that's
only half of it the other half is
entering into a relationship with this
overflow yes and being able to use it as
an evaluative device to analyze the rest
of your life to some degree yeah there's
this sense in which you have access to
this numinous fullness and that can
become the standard for action then yes
that even scarcity could be ordered by
your experience of a numinous fullness
but if it isn't then it's kind of going
in the opposite direction from that yeah
I agree with that completely I think
that's very right I see that also that
even people have even when you were
doing the first stage what you said like
shifting from intimacy within the
overflow to intimacy with the overflow
like that's the thing I'm trying to sort
of work into circling practices because
the circling tends to be intimacy within
the overflow but there isn't very been
trying to say well zoom out and then try
to become cultivate intimacy with the
overflow because that's a different
thing and then like you said it can then
become an enacted present normative
field right by which you can explore
things cultivate discernment you know
try to get new insight into how you're
formulating your identity in the world
exactly but it is telling sorry this is
not meant to be self emotional it is
telling that you know I have to say that
right it's like people can very easily
and I think you've kept putting your
finger back on people can very easily
get entrenched with just being in the
overflow and never stepping back to come
into a right relationship and intimacy
with the overflow itself and I think
that's a big part of dialectical
practice about bringing that if you if
you're getting it through conversational
if you're experiencing overflow in a
conversational discourse manner and part
of that electic is to do exactly that to
shift off of intimacy within or
were float to intimacy with overflow
yeah the most generous definition of
religion I think involves a social
process which calls us to do that
yes which cites something that's
additional - or even beyond mysticism in
terms of its responsibility for engaging
that like even even what we just did in
discussing now if the numinous overflow
right we're there now faithful to the
Lord so to speak right we we're invoking
we're referencing it we're honoring it
calling it forth yes I think
faithfulness to the logos is exactly at
the heart of Dia logos by way up by
means of it right it's a faithfulness
like we talked about earlier to the
logos and especially insofar as the
faithfulness to the logos affords people
- well called the big wisdom and love
etcetera yes
I totally think that I should get going
there with certain mystic states and
certain psychedelic states thinking all
the way back for Humanity put people in
a situation where I think they see that
sort of even visually like I recently
didn't talk on entheogens and it's not a
huge part of my life but I've had a few
interesting experiences some of them the
sense of the numinous other that comes
forth in the exchange no it is almost
something you behold right then the
languaging of the divine person makes a
lot of sense what you see there's some
other and you actually see it it's not
just in you and it's not just in the
other person no you have this experience
a Buddhist class as well as in something
was sneaking out the back of my head and
also looking at me through the teachers
eyes very much very much you know Chris
and I and the chapter we wrote on gnosis
in the second person we talked about
this as the third factor like the third
you've heard it the third man factor
where people are in situations and they
people sense another presence other than
the physically and I don't mean anything
supernatural I think was in Shackleton
even though they were on an expedition
and they all sort of
they had a sense presence that was not
any of the people there Geiger has a
whole book called the third man factor
this is well documented and the third
man factor capacity definitely is
activated when you're doing these
circling practices and Chris and I call
it therefore the write the emergence of
the third factor or Geist because we're
trying to get something the German word
is nice because it moves between mind
and spirit and sort of you know it's
much it's much more comprehensive than
any of the terms that we typically used
I think yeah I think people get the
sense of that and they start to relate
to it as an entity interesting in their
in sort of recent psychological
cognitive scientist literature and
philosophical literature on what is
called we agency that emergent factor
that above and beyond us the we the
distributed cognition is doing something
they talked about it now as like like a
philosophical zombie it an intelligence
emerges there's no consciousness to it
right but there's an intelligence that
emerges and and it seems to be a real
sort of a real sort of thing in that it
can solve problems that the individuals
can't solve so I do think there's good
sort of but there's good emerging
cognitive science to underpin everything
we're talking about here and therefore
help us get a better relationship to it
but I'm also intrigued by what you said
about certain states that becomes
synesthetic it goes from being a sense
presence to being a visualized presence
or an encountered presence I remember I
won't say when because I don't want to
uh there was a time in my life very far
removed from this time in my life let's
say in which I did psilocybin and did
Tai Chi Chuan and she is kind of like
the internalization it's the sensed
presence of the DAO right if you know is
imaginal transductive thing between you
and the world and it uses all these
musical metaphors that we've been using
you know all this
and so I I have powerful experiences of
that plate regularly right and that's
how you learn how to fight with their
didn't stuff like it and there's nothing
magical in in the supernatural istic
sense but when when I when I was doing
it there was two thirds two aspects of
it that were really cool so I saw a blue
fire i vision I had a synesthetic
experience of the Qi as blue fire moving
all over my body and if what was really
what really kicked it into high gear is
there was this little girl and she came
and she was staring at me with like
saucer eyes and somehow I almost fancied
that she could see the flames as well
because you know state she was
definitely picking up on something more
that was happening to me than what was
was normally present because she was
looking at me with and again this is
this is not about me she was looking at
the event that I was involved in with
Wonder almost ah and was like whoa
that's a very powerful experience so
yeah I totally think that would there
are places where we sin aesthetically
start to visualize or even how here you
know that third presence yeah my
girlfriend and I always have to reach
for this we just call it the third in
general yeah like me that our
relationship is playing a role in our
relationship in addition to the rule
that we reach playing yeah and it really
doesn't you can't really describe it
properly without that additional factor
yeah and this is why I mean part of the
reason why I've spent so much time
trying to get out this notion of
transductive 'ti is because the the what
we're talking about is not sort of
objective and it's not merely subjective
it's transductive in a really really
powerful way the relation itself what
we're saying is the relation itself not
the relati but the relation itself
becomes right real actual actual izing
and present it's acting
the Galatian itself and I so I think I
think that's really really important and
again I've mentioned to you this before
I'm just impressed by how people from
various backgrounds often very secular
both in the religious and and you know
sense and the more general sense we have
now they will talk about this with
religious language just spontaneously
because no other language is close
enough to hit it and that tells us
something that tells us something about
what we need to be doing leave me and I
gotta get going okay
sorry that's kind of a shot I did try to
mention it a few minutes earlier but you
didn't quite hear me and then you said
something that was really interesting in
performing and we got caught up in it
going indefinitely I'm sure next time
yeah so I would very much like to make
this public are you okay with it I think
this is a valuable conversation I'm fine
with that
thank you great topics anybody should be
happy to hear them I mean I really like
like I said I liked your way of well you
have discernment and I just want to
honor that in you so thank you very much
thank you John I appreciate that
oh you're welcome okay so well I'll see
I'll talk to you again soon
yeah well we'll set something else up
soon okay take care